Student Body Collection UA029
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Student Body Collection
1870 -- 1989
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Miller, Russell E.
UA029
1.04 Linear Feet 3 boxes
Arrangement
This collection is organized in one series: Student body.
Biographical / Historical
Russell Elliott Miller was a Professor of History, University Historian and Archivist of Tufts University, and author of "Light on the Hill, A History of Tufts College from 1852 to 1952" and the second volume "Light on the Hill, A History of Tufts University since 1952." He was born in Bloomington, Minnesota, on April 25, 1916, to one of the last pioneer families in the Minnesota prairie. His mother spoke Dakota Sioux, which she had learned as a child. He received a B.A. in Education in 1937 and an M.A. in political science in 1939, both from the University of Florida at Gainesville. From 1942 to 1946, he served in the Army Air Corps as an enlisted man, rising to the rank of technical sergeant. Initially with personnel and classification, he was finally assigned to the historical section (intelligence) at the headquarters of the troop carrier command. In 1948 he earned a Master of Arts in history from Princeton University and came to Tufts that same year.
In 1952 he received a PhD from Princeton, and in 1964 Tufts appointed him Professor of History and University Historian and archivist. He taught courses ranging from the history of western civilization to the history of the American frontier. In 1966, he published "Light on the Hill, A History of Tufts College from 1852 to 1952." That year he received the Distinguished Service Award from the Tufts Alumni Association and became an honorary member of Phi Beta Kappa. In 1975 he became the Walter S. Dickson Professor of English and American History and chaired the Department of History from then until 1980. He was voted Emeritus Professor of English and American History in 1981 and received an honorary Doctor of Letters degree in 1983. In 1986, he completed the second volume of Tufts history, "Light on the Hill II, A History of Tufts University since 1952."
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains information about the student body, activism, alcohol, drugs, and foreign students on campus. Materials include newspaper clippings, pictures, correspondence, reports, statistics, and academic and student papers.
Custodial History
The "Student Body" collection was created by Russell Miller, possibly while preparing "Light on the Hill," his history of Tufts College. The material was assembled from various departments. No attempt has been made to restore the original order of this material.
Student life; Student activism; Health and Safety
- Student body, 1870 -- 1989; UA029.001; 1.25 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series was created by Russell Miller while preparing his history of Tufts, Light on the Hill. All material was organized by subject and no attempt has been made to restore the original order of the material. The series contains information about activism, alcohol, drugs, and foreign students through the medium of newspaper clippings, papers on the topics, pictures, memos and correspondence.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - General, 1870 -- 1981; UA029.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
    Content Warning
    This folder contains materials that are sexist, racist, and antisemitic. For more information on DCA's content warning policy please visit our website.
  - Activism (1), 1969 -- 1984; UA029.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Activism (2), 1969 -- 1984; UA029.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Alcohol, 1977 -- 1980; UA029.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Chapel, 1928 -- 1936; UA029.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Sit-in over Dreier tenure case, 1983; UA029.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Drugs, 1970 -- 1989; UA029.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - Foreign Student Advisor, 1963 -- 1968; UA029.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - Divestment -- general, 1977 -- 1979; UA029.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Divestment -- general, 1977 -- 1979; UA029.001.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - Divestment -- sit-in, 1985; UA029.001.002.00003 (Box 2)
  - Housing, UA029.001.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - Minorities (1), 1968 -- 1972; UA029.001.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - Minorities, (2), 1968 -- 1975; UA029.001.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - Opinion, 1926 -- 1972; UA029.001.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - Student strike and anti-war protests, 1969 -- 1972; UA029.001.003.00005 (Box 3)
  - Veterans, UA029.001.003.00006 (Box 3)